Finding aid for the Marsha Epstein Papers LSC.2220
UCLA Library Special Collections
Marsha Epstein papers
1945-2010
UCLA Library Special Collections
Epstein, Marsha
LSC.2220
34 Linear Feet (43 boxes)
Marsha Epstein is a lifelong activist for LGBT rights, and an advocate for the inclusion of bisexual accounts as part of the history of the gay rights movement. This collection contains both personal and professional materials representing Marsha Epstein's life from her childhood to adulthood. Included are her research materials from many years of medical practice as well as personal correspondence, materials from various schools and ephemera from her Jewish, women's and bisexual activism throughout the Los Angeles area.
Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
Acquisition Information
Provenance unknown. This collection is part of an outreach and collection-building partnership between the June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives, the UCLA Center for the Study of Women (CSW) and the UCLA Library.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 7566257
Biography
Marsha Epstein has been a lifelong activist for LGBT rights, and an advocate for the inclusion of bisexual accounts as part of the history of the gay rights movement. She is a subject in the documentary, On These Shoulders We Stand, an historical account of early gay life and activism in Los Angeles told by the people who lived it. She is also an active volunteer and participant in the Los Angeles Jewish community, through her work with Beth Chayim Chadasim.
She received her Bachelor's Degree from Reed College in Portland, Oregon, and attended medical school at UC San Francisco where she received a Master of Public Medicine. She studied Health in Epidemiology at UC Berkeley and completed a residency in General Preventive Medicine. She also completed a Fellowship in Family Planning at UCLA and started working in family planning, performing abortions for Los Angeles County for a brief period. She had a private practice for four years and after the birth of her son, eventually went to work for the Los Angeles County Public Health System for twenty eight years. She served as a District Health Officer for thirteen years, Area Medical Director for twelve years, and then transferred to Chronic Disease Prevention. She developed a tobacco cessation continuing education program online, also serving to educate primary care doctors throughout Los Angeles County about tobacco cessation.
In 1974-1975, she worked for the women's clinic at the Gay and Lesbian Services Center in Los Angeles. From 1975-1979 she was the Medical Director of Herself Health Clinic, a women's clinic run by a cooperative of radical lesbians for the women in the community.
Scope and Content
The collection contains both personal and professional materials representing Marsha Epstein's life from her childhood to adulthood. Included are her research materials from many years of medical practice as well as personal correspondence, materials from various schools and ephemera from her Jewish, women's and bisexual activism throughout the Los Angeles area.
Physicians -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archival resources; Epstein, Marsha
- Los Angeles Public Health Leadership Institute, 2007; printed paper (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Telecommuting, 2007; printed paper (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Training manual and certification documentation for telecommuting work.
- Los Angeles County Reimbursement Paperwork, 2003-2009; printed paper (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Personal correspondence, No date; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Personal correspondence, 1969; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Personal correspondence, 1967; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Recovery program documentation, 2005-2012; printed paper (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Compulsive Eaters Anonymous and AL - ANON.
- Family finances, 1986-2011; printed paper (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Genealogy materials, 1988-1989; printed paper (Box 2, Folder 1)
- HIV research study, 1988; printed paper (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Memorials and obituaries, 1988-2012; printed paper (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Personal correspondence, 1965-1966; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Family finances, 1968-2012; printed paper (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Family finances, 1968-2012; printed paper (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Mailings, 1980-2012; printed paper (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Mailings from various non-profits and organizations soliciting help and support or participation.
- Personal correspondence, 1968; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 2, Folder 7)
- School of Public Health, 1971; photos, printed paper (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Photos as well as address listings and contact information for students and fellows.
- Judaism, 1971-2011; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Published materials about Jewish faith and diaspora.
- Board of Medical Quality Assurance, 1980; printed paper (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Certification materials.
- California Psychological Survey, 1975; printed paper (Box 3, Folder 4)
- UCLA Family Planning Course, 1977; printed paper (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Course materials.
- UCLA Family Planning Course, 1977; printed paper (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Certificates, 1984-2000; printed paper (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Certificates of accomplishment, certification and recognition for Marsha Epstein.
- Letters of commendation, 1987-2007; printed paper (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Workers compensation, 1988-1994; printed paper (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Letters of commendation, 1988-2004; printed paper (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Delmy, 1984-2001; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Includes contact information, reference letter and status update of Ana Aguilar's Immigration, a former employee of Marsha Epstein.
- Pregnancy referrals, 1985; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Life insurance, 1990-2000; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Financial statements, 1994-1999; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Travel documents, 1994-2011; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Clippings, 1997-2009; printed paper, photocopy (Box 4, Folder 6)
- American Medical Association, 1999; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Beth Shir Sholom, 1999; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Research materials (AIDS), 1999; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Mailings, 1999-2000; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Disability insurance, 1999-2010; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Beth Chadim Chadashim, 2000-2010; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Certificates, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Living trust, 2005; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Mileage, 2006; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Workshop materials, No date; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Correspondence - Tucker Health Center, 1985-2000; printed paper (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Journals, 1994-1995; handwritten notes (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Personal correspondence, 1999; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Financial information, 1990-2000; printed paper (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Research materials, 1980-2010; printed paper (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1984-2000; printed paper (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Research materials (Psychology and depression), 1978-2005; printed paper (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Research materials (Psychiatry), 1979-1994; printed paper (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Research materials (Pain), 1985-1996; printed paper (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Research materials (anxiety), 1987-1992; printed paper (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Research materials (gastro-intestinal irritable bowel syndrome), 1994; printed paper (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Research materials (ostheoporosis), 2005; printed paper (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Research materials (mental health), 2005; printed paper (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Jewish holidays, 2012-2013; printed paper (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Research materials (medical history), No date; printed paper (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Research materials (teaching materials), 1972-1983; printed paper (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Research materials (sleep), 1972-2006; printed paper (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Research materials (infant mortality), 1973-1980; printed paper (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Research materials (abortion), 1974-1990; printed paper (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Research materials (sports medicine), 1979; printed paper (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Research materials (impaired physicians), 1980; printed paper (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Research materials (birth control), 1985-1987; printed paper (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Research materials (chronic fatigue syndrome), 1992-2000; printed paper (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Research materials (depression), 1997; printed paper (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Research materials (aging), 1965-1997; printed paper (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Research materials (anthropology), 1967-1969; printed paper (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Research materials (obstetrics), 1969-1983; printed paper (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Research materials (urology), 1969-1996; printed paper (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Research materials (diet), 1970-1985; printed paper (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Research materials (allergies), 1970-2003; printed paper (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Research materials (ecology), 1971-1973; printed paper (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Research materials (herbal remedies), 1984; printed paper (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Research materials (bulimia), 1984; printed paper (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Research materials (arthritis), 1990; printed paper (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Research materials (endocrine), No date; printed paper (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Undergraduate work, 1964-1965; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 9, Folder 1)
  Includes: Thesis "Students on the Relaxation of a Molluscan 'Catch' Muscle" 1965 Personal evaluation of the WECHE Work Study Program inMental Illness and Retardation 1964 Calendar
- MediCal Yearbooks, 1966-1968; printed paper, cloth bound books (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Research materials (miscellaneous), 1990-2010; printed paper (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Newsletters, 2002-2003; printed paper (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Journal of the American Medical Women's Association, 2003-2004; printed paper (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Chronic Disease: Notes and Reports, 2003-2004; printed paper (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Greeting cards, 2007-2011; printed paper, notecard (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Greeting cards, 2004-2006; printed paper, notecard (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Greeting cards, 2000-2003; printed paper, notecard (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Greeting cards, 1993-1996; printed paper, notecard (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Los Angeles County Performance Evaluations, 1989-2010; printed paper (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Temple Shir Shalom, 1990-1995; printed paper (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Job search materials, 1991; printed paper (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Testimonies on fraud/licensing, 2001-2003; printed paper (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Photos - Tucker Health Center, 2005; color photographs (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Interviewing, charting skills, No date; printed paper (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Ephemera, 1970-1989; printed paper, bound books, three ring binders (Box 12)
  Weigh Watchers materials, cookbooks, binders, meal tracking supplies.
- Correspondence, 1977-2013; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 13)
- Correspondence, 1960-1976; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 14)
- Watercolor journal, 1981-1985; watercolor (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Calendar (Paula Smith), 1989; printed paper (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Calendars, 1992-1994; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Water journals, 2001-2011; watercolor (Box 15, Folder 4)
- ClassAct Cleaning services (Paula Smith), No date; printed paper (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Licensing/documentation, 1978-2011; printed paper (Box 16, Folder 1)
- Certificates, 2008-2009; printed paper (Box 16, Folder 2)
- Human resources (employment records), 1995-2005; printed paper (Box 16, Folder 3)
- Electronic Questionnaires for Investigative Processing (E-QIP), 2007; printed paper (Box 16, Folder 4)
- University of California San Francisco - Occupational Health, 1989-1990; printed paper (Box 16, Folder 5)
- Passover/seder, 1977-2011; printed paper (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Research materials (neurology, neurosurgery), 1966-2005; printed paper (Box 17, Folder 1)
- Research materials (surgery), 1967-1972; printed paper (Box 17, Folder 2)
- Research materials (gastrointestinal, ulcers), 1968-1991; printed paper (Box 17, Folder 3)
- Research materials (hematology), 1968-1969; printed paper (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Research materials (obstetrics - social impact), 1971-1991; printed paper (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Research materials (gastrointestinal, diarrhea), 1974-1982; printed paper (Box 17, Folder 7)
- Research materials (gastrointestinal), 1974-1996; printed paper (Box 17, Folder 8)
- Research materials (meditation), 1975-1985; printed paper (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Research materials (meditation), 1975-1985; printed paper (Box 17, Folder 9)
- Medical documents (personal), 1966-1970; printed paper (Box 18, Folder 1)
- Calendars, 1972; printed paper (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Source catalog (3), 1974; printed paper (Box 18, Folder 3)
- Calendar, 1991; printed paper (Box 18, Folder 4)
- Correspondence (Paula), 1994-2003; handwritten notes (Box 18, Folder 5)
- Union (Medical Practitioners), 2002; printed paper (Box 18, Folder 6)
- Guestbook, 2010; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 18, Folder 7)
- Department of Health Services (Personnel), 1987; printed paper (Box 19, Folder 1)
- Nutrition research, 1993-1999; printed paper (Box 19, Folder 2)
- Diversity, 1994-2004; printed paper (Box 19, Folder 3)
  Includes manuals and guides to diversity and cultural competence for medical service providers.
- Cultural/spiritual assessment manual, 2000; printed paper (Box 19, Folder 4)
- Search and rescue techniques, 1996; printed paper (Box 19, Folder 4)
- CERT (Community Emergency Response Team) Program, 1996; printed paper (Box 19, Folder 5)
  Instruction manuals, organizational charts, research materials and contact information.
- DMO (Disaster Medical Operations), 1996; printed paper (Box 19, Folder 6)
- Mortality reports, 2003-2006; printed paper (Box 19, Folder 8)
- Disaster preparedness - DMAT (Disaster Medical Assistance Team), 2005; printed paper (Box 19, Folder 9)
- Community health work review, 1972; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 21, Folder 1)
- Sex literature and catalogs, 1972; printed paper, handwritten notes, carbon copy (Box 21, Folder 2)
- University of California San Francisco nurse practitioners, 1973; newsprint, handwritten notes (Box 21, Folder 3)
- University of California Los Angeles abortion clinic, 1973-1974; printed paper, handwritten notes, photocopy (Box 21, Folder 4)
- Birth control literature, 1974; printed paper, newsprint, photocopy (Box 21, Folder 5)
- Women's health, 1974-1977; printed paper, carbon copy (Box 21, Folder 6)
- Women's health clinics, 1974-1977; printed paper, newsprint (Box 21, Folder 7)
- University of California Los Angeles family planning nurse practitioners program (class 7), 1976; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 21, Folder 8)
- Cervical cap study, 1981; printed paper (Box 21, Folder 9)
- STD site audit, 1991; printed paper, photocopy, handwritten notes (Box 21, Folder 10)
- Marsha and Paula (step study), No date; handwritten notes (Box 21, Folder 11)
- Miscellaneous forms, No date; printed paper (Box 21, Folder 12)
  Forms from various studies, not filled out.
- Boarding passes, No date; airplane boarding passes, photocopy (Box 21, Folder 13)
- Pre/post abortion counseling notes and script, No date; printed paper (Box 21, Folder 14)
- Abortion clinic forms (various), No date; printed paper (Box 21, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1978-1980; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 22, Folder 1)
- Continuing medical education (CME) forms, 2009; printed paper (Box 22, Folder 2)
- Mother's death (correspondence and planning), 2010; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 22, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 2012-2013; handwritten notes, printed paper (Box 22, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous personal, No date; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 22, Folder 5)
- Twelve step literature, No date; printed paper (Box 22, Folder 6)
  Programs, handouts for different twelve step programs for substance abuse and other forms of addiction.
- Flyers and calendars, No date; printed paper, photocopy, handwritten notes (Box 22, Folder 7)
- Research materials (hospital policies), No date; printed paper, photocopy (Box 22, Folder 8)
- Women's periodicals, 1963-1973; newsprint, photocopy (Box 23, Folder 1)
  Off Our Backs Volume II, Number 6 February - March 1972 The Every Other Weekly Volume I, No. 15 November 10, 1970 Clippings from The Guardian, Ms., etc.
- Student health program, 1967; printed paper, photocopy (Box 23, Folder 2)
- University of California Los Angeles family planning nurse practitioner program, 1976; printed paper, photocopy, carbon copy (Box 23, Folder 3)
  Grant materials, descriptions of programs, correspondence.
- University of California Los Angeles family planning program (preceptorship), 1976; printed paper (Box 23, Folder 4)
- Letters of recommendation (from Marsha Epstein), 1977-2001; printed paper (Box 23, Folder 5)
- Board of medical quality assurance review committee, 1978-1982; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 23, Folder 6)
- Reed College evaluations, 1979-1980; printed paper, photocopy (Box 23, Folder 7)
- Affiliations/memberships, 1979-2000; printed paper (Box 23, Folder 8)
  Information about Marsha Epsteins various affiliations and memberships.
- Correspondence, 1980-1990; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 23, Folder 9)
- Board of medical assurance, 1981; printed paper (Box 23, Folder 10)
- Teleplay - "If Men Could Get Pregnant...", 1982; printed paper, photocopy (Box 23, Folder 11)
- Sale of practice, 1983; printed paper (Box 23, Folder 12)
- Papers (by Marsha Epstein), 1987; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 23, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1991; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 23, Folder 14)
- Independent HIV research, 1992; photocopy, handwritten notes (Box 23, Folder 15)
- Medical advisory board (Clinica Romera), 1993; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 23, Folder 16)
- Medical board (Dr. Sison), 1997; printed paper (Box 23, Folder 17)
  Correspondence, reports.
- Medical fraud notes/slides, 2001; printed paper (Box 23, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 1970-1972; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 24, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1973; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 24, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1974; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 24, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1975; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 24, Folder 4)
- Clinics, 2001-2002; printed paper (Box 24, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 2010-2012; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 24, Folder 6)
- Cartoons, No date; photocopy (Box 24, Folder 7)
- Manuals and materials, 1991-2003; spiral bound binders, printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 25)
  Manuals and training materials from workshops throughout California. Includes a binder focused on Challenges in Psychiatry from 1994, Occupational and Environmental Medicine from 1991, Substance Abuse Training in Tarzana and Addiction Medicine from 1993.
- Bank statements, 1968-1974; printed paper (Box 26)
  Bank statements for Marsha Epstein.
- Correspondence, 1959; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 27, Folder 1)
  Personal correspondence
- Correspondence, 1960; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 27, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1963; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 27, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1964; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 27, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1965; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 27, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1970-2010; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 27, Folder 6)
- Certificates, 1971-2006; printed paper (Box 27, Folder 7)
  Various certificates of award and recognition honoring Marsha Epstein's work in the medical community.
- Marriage contracts and certificates, 1975; printed paper (Box 27, Folder 8)
  Marriage documentation for Marsha Epstein and Tariq Mahmood.
- Paystubs, 1982-2010; printed paper (Box 27, Folder 9)
  Contains paystubs for Marsha Epstein.
- Miscellaneous work documents, 1990-2001; printed paper (Box 27, Folder 10)
  Parts of various guides and programs from medical conferences and gatherings.
- Community conference feedback, 2006; printed paper (Box 27, Folder 11)
  Summary report of a community conference on the status of healthcare.
- Tobacco continuing medical education, 2008; printed paper, photocopy (Box 27, Folder 12)
  Articles and reports focused on continuing medical education for tobacco addiction and smoking cessation.
- Retirement information, 2010; printed paper (Box 27, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 2012; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 27, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1961; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 27, Folder 15)
- Periodicals, 1972-1974; magazines (Box 28, Folder 1)
  Psychology Today Jan 1974 The Female Experience 1973 Redbook 1976 How do You Feel about Being a Woman? The Results of a Redbook Questionnaire January 1993 Redbook Januray 1973
- Calendars and diaries, 1976-2009; spiral bound notebooks and printed paper (Box 28, Folder 2)
  Personal calendars and diaries documenting Marsha Epstein's daily activities.
- Institutional review board (Los Angeles County Department of Health), 2012; printed paper (Box 28, Folder 3)
  Contains a Report of the Institutional Review Board on behalf of the Los Angeles County Department of Health.
- Research materials (cost saving), 1990-1998; photocopy, printed paper (Box 28, Folder 4)
- Working titles and operational chart, 1992-1998; printed paper, handwritten notes, photocopy (Box 28, Folder 5)
  National Disaster Medical System organizational charts, work flow documents and other institutional information.
- Research materials (dermatology), 1965-1975; clippings, printed paper, photocopy (Box 28, Folder 6)
- Research materials (medical education), 1970-1975; printed paper, clippings, photocopy (Box 28, Folder 7)
- Research materials (fibromyalgia), 2006; clippings, printed paper, photocopy (Box 28, Folder 8)
- Research materials (eye), 1970-1996; printed paper, clippings, photocopy (Box 28, Folder 9)
- Research materials (ear, nose and throat), 1969-2010; printed paper, clippings, photocopy (Box 28, Folder 10)
- Research materials (cardiovascular), 1965-2005; printed paper, clippings, photocopy (Box 28, Folder 11)
- Research materials (breast and ovarian cancer), 1997-1998; printed paper, clippings, photocopy (Box 28, Folder 12)
- Workers compensation documentation, 2006-2007; printed paper (Box 28, Folder 13)
  Legal and institutional information focused on Workers compensation.
- Research materials (addiction medicine), 1990-2000; printed paper, handwritten notes, photocopy (Box 28, Folder 14)
- Psychotherapy business, 1990-2000; printed paper, handwritten notes, photocopy (Box 28, Folder 15)
  Contains research materials, notes on consultations and business plans.
- Work notes, 2010; printed paper, handwritten notes (Box 29, Folder 1)
  Contains notes from professional activities.
- School awards and records, 1956-1993; handwritten notes, printed paper, carbon paper (Box 29, Folder 2)
  Awards and grades from various phases of Marsha Epstein's schooling.
- Photographs, 2001-2004; color photographs of varying sizes (Box 29, Folder 3)
  Photographs from vacations and various activities with friends and family.
- Tickets and programs, 1963-2012; printed papers (Box 29, Folder 4)
  Contains tickets and programs to various cultural events, concerts and activities.
- Wedding materials, 1976; printed paper, photocopy (Box 29, Folder 5)
  Contains wedding planning materials, invitations and details.
- Correspondence, 1966; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 29, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1967; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 29, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1968; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 29, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1969; handwritten notes, envelopes (Box 29, Folder 9)